这是太阳系的明星秀
It is the show-stopper of our Solar System,
闪亮的外表吸引着大量的爱好者
basking in its own glow, it seduces all admirers.
但是 美丽外表下隐藏着恶魔
However, it is a beauty with a mean streak.
土星是一个环绕着冰质光环的气态星球
It's a massive, frigid ball of gas,
光环以40000英里每小时(64000千米每小时)旋转
surrounded by icy rings hurdling at 40,000 miles an hour.
土星有着非常疯狂的气象
It is a planet of violent weather,
极地的飓风面积比美国还大
with a polar storm bigger than the United States of America.
土星的一些气象是太阳系中最强大的
Saturn has some of the most powerful weather in the Solar System.
闪电的能量比地球上的大100万倍
The lightning could be a million times more powerful than here on Earth.
不过土星的卫星更吸引人
But its moons are even more exciting.
恩克拉多斯(土卫二)上的喷泉 喷出几百英里高的水汽
The geysers on Enceladus are erupting water vapour hundreds of miles into the air
因为这里引力很小 且没有大气
because there's much lower gravity there and the fact that there's no atmosphere holding them in.
另外一颗土星卫星有大气 海洋和山脉
Another has an atmosphere with oceans and mountains.
也许某颗卫星上会有生命
Could life exist on one of these moons?
土星 光环王者
Saturn: Lord of the Rings.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
历史频道·宇宙第一季第8集 土星 光环王者
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：射手网 调校：TIAN@CMCT 招募Q号: 76846146
如果说宇宙中有一颗行星
If there is one planet
象征着美丽 神秘和奇异
that represents the majesty, mystery and awe of the Universe,
那一定是土星
it is Saturn.
科学家们也为之激动
It stirs emotion even from scientists who are stunned
被这完美宇宙奇观惊动
by its cosmic perfection.
你不可否认土星是这宇宙中最美丽的
You've got to hand it to Saturn for being the most beautiful thing out there.
土星是我最喜欢的行星 我一直用望远镜观察它
It's been my favourite planet since I first saw it through the telescope.
尽管看起来宁静安详
While it looks sleepy and serene,
这颗太阳系第6行星其实并不平静
the sixth planet from the Sun is anything but.
美丽的外表下隐藏了一个发电机的心
Saturn is a dynamo whose beauty is skin-deep.
土星上极其寒冷
Saturn's an absolutely frigid place.
不要想着登陆土星
You wouldn't want to step out on the surface.
首先它没有固体表面
For one reason, you'd fall 'cause there is no surface,
其次也会立即冻死
but secondly, you'd freeze to death instantly.
土星是一个大量氢气和氦气
Saturn is a hunk of hydrogen and helium
围绕自轴高速旋转成型的行星
that races around its axis distorting its shape.
观察专业意大利比萨制作过程
When you watch a professional toss of pizza,
手抛饼底 旋转扁平成型
as it spins around it flattens out.
同样的道理 由于很高的旋转
So it's the same kind of idea, because it's spinning so rapidly
土星有一点扁平 中间鼓起来
it's actually sort of squashed, sort of bulges in the middle.
称之为"扁球"
It's called an"oblate spheroid".
尽管体型比地球大很多
Even though it's much more massive than our own planet,
土星上的重力比地球还略小
you'd actually weigh slightly less on Saturn that you do on Earth.
一个150磅(68千克)的人 在土星上只有137磅(62千克)
A 150-pound human would weigh only 137 pounds on Saturn.
是因为土星密度很低
That's because Saturn has such a low density.
是太阳系中唯一密度低于水的行星
The only planet in the Solar System less dense than water.
土星如此臃肿
Saturn is so bloated,
绝大部分体积都是气体
the gases take up so much space compared to the total amount of mass in Saturn,
于是密度低于水
that its density is less than one.
因此假如我们有一个巨大的海
So if we could get somehow some…really big ocean
把土星放进去 它会飘浮着
in put Saturn in it, it would float.
体型上土星是太阳系第二大行星
Saturn is the second largest planet in our Solar System.
是个气体的巨行星
It is a gas giant,
大量的氢和氦
a mass of hydrogen and helium
有地球750倍大
750 times the size of Earth.
一天只有10.6个小时
A day on the planet is 10,6 hours long.
绕太阳一周需要29.5个地球年
And it takes 29.5 Earth years to orbit the Sun.
拥有48个已命名的卫星
It has 48 named moons.
土星存在于太阳系几乎45亿年了
Saturn has been around for 4.5 billion years.
硬质核心由碳颗粒积聚而成
It formed by accreting carbon dust, particle by particle, into a rocky core
大约有几个地球大
several times the size of Earth.
吸引着外面大量的氢和氦
Then, it was able to attract gases, like hydrogen and helium,
巨大重力下这些气体坍塌了
which collapsed under gravity.
由于开始坍塌 气体被压缩
As things started collapsing, this cloud began to compress,
旋转也变的更快
it began rotating more rapidly,
沿自转轴方向上 顶部到底部是不旋转的
but along its axis, from let's say top to bottom, it wasn't rotating,
因此在重力作用下自行坍塌了
so it was free to collapse under the force of gravity.
角动量守恒定理
It's called the conservation of angular momentum.
最初在溜冰场上被展示
A principle on display at your local ice ring.
如果你伸开你的腿和双臂速度会变慢
If you push your arms out if you're an ice skater, you'll go more slowly.
收紧你的双臂
If you pull your arms in,
靠近你的旋转轴
then you'll be more concentrated towards the axis of rotation
你会转的更快
and you'll have to spin faster.
行星在收缩时也会这样
And that's just what happens for a planet as it condenses.
土星在圆盘坍塌过程中旋转起来
A spinning Saturn came out of this collapsed disk.
土星是太阳系中
The feature that has made Saturn the most iconic planet in our Solar System,
最壮丽的标志
is its majestic,
拥有明亮的光环
shimmering rings.
光环不可思议的大 直径约173000英里(280000千米)
They are incredibly big, 173,000 miles in diameter.
比21个地球排列还宽
Wider than 21 Earths side by side.
巨大的光环高速旋转 从一端到另一端只需约2天
So it would take you 2 days in a really fast rocket ship to get from one side of the rings to the other. They're huge.
但是这些巨大的光环不可思议的薄
However, these huge rings also are unbelievably thin.
只有65英尺(20米)厚
Measuring about 65 feet.
如果从旁边观看几乎看不到
When viewed from the side, they virtually disappear.
厚度大约只相当于
They are no thicker than about one,
两层楼高
maybe two storeys in a modern day building.
就像一张纸
They're paper-thin in comparison.
看起来像个完美的固体圆盘
The rings may look like perfect solid disks,
实际上却是由无数碎片
however, they are actually made up of billions of pieces
散布而构成
of space debris.
多大的碎片？
But what exactly are they?
这些大量的冰冷碎片
They are countless icy bodies, ranging in size from…
大的相当于房屋大
objects as big as houses all the way down to the finest,
小的仅有犹他州滑雪场的雪花那么大
powdery snow, you might ski on in Utah.
都由冰块组成
And they're made of water ice.
碎片散布又互相碰撞
They're particles that have been pulverized, so they've smashed into each other,
碎成更小的颗粒
they've broken up into many, many little particles.
呆在土星环里 你会被击成蜂窝
If you were to be inside those rings it would be like a beehive.
到处都是密布的蜂群
They're all over the place, like bees in a swarm.
不要派飞船到危险的土星环上去
It's a hostile place, you do not want to try to put a spacecraft through those rings.
这些碎片高速旋转
And these particles spin very fast.
旋转速度大约20000至40000英里每小时(32000至64000千米每小时)
And they're screaming around the planet at 20 to 40 mph.
环内部比环外部的速度快的多
The inner rings spin faster than the outer rings,
原因是
and there's a reason for that.
开普勒定理表明--如果以圆形轨道环绕中心旋转
That if you're gonna orbit in a circle around a central body, Kepler's laws say,
越靠近中心旋转越快 越远离中心旋转越慢
if you're close up you move really fast, if you're far away, you move really slow.
如果一颗细沙大小颗粒
If a particle the size of a grain of sand
以超音速击中太空船
moving at hypersonic speed were to strike a spacecraft,
不亚于一枪击中太空船
it would be like a shotgun blast at point blank range.
环外的空间
And you get outside the rings,
相当宁静
things are much quieter.
如果去参观土星
If you want to take a country drive around Saturn,
请绕过土星环 不要接触它
go this way,instead of following the rings.
为什么说环是土星最神秘之处呢？
Why the rings are there is one of the planet's great mysteries.
环在很久以前可能是两颗很近卫星
The rings might have once been some of Saturn's moons that got too close
碰撞并碎裂了
and smashed into each other.
土星的引力维持着这些碎片
The fractured pieces were held by the planet's gravity
形成土星环
to become its rings.
基于另外一个理论
According to another theory,
也许一个巨大的高速物体
something big and fast might have crashed
撞击了某个土星卫星
into one of Saturn's many moons.
碎片被土星引力留下
The broken shards were sucked in by gravity
旋转而形成土星环
and fell into orbit forming the rings.
尽管科学家们对环的形成意见不那么统一
Although scientists disagree as to how the rings were formed,
对土星环的发现者却没有异议
they do agree as to who first studied them.
1610年天文学家伽利略
In 1610, the Florentine astronomer Galileo Galilei,
第一个观测到土星的光环
first noted the rings of Saturn.
他看到这些固定在土星周围的光亮物质
He saw these little things sticking out on the side of the planet.
不知道是什么东西 像很多天文学家那样
He had no idea what they were, so like any good astronomer,
伽利略记录了他的发现
Galileo kept a journal, and he wanted to write into his journal what he had seen,
但是 没有具体说明
but he didn't have a word for it,
因此他的笔记里没有任何词语说明
so in his journal, right in with the words,
只有一幅图示
he drew in a drawing in place of a noun,
这就是他所画的
and this is what he drew.
土星在这里  这两个是他发现的东西
Here's Saturn, and here's these two things.
遗憾的是伽利略并不确切知道这是什么
Unfortunately Galileo never really figured out what it was.
只能等今后的天文学家继续探索
We had to wait for a later astronomer to do that.
45年后荷兰物理学家惠更斯
45 years later, a Dutch physicist, Christiaan Huygens,
找到了答案
had an answer.
他认识到这些不仅仅是一个圆环而是几条圆环
He knew that there wasn't just one ring, but several giant rings.
如今我们知道里面有7个环区
Today, there are seven know ring regions.
A环B环C环
There's the A-ring, the B-ring and the C-ring.
是3个最主要的环
So those are the three main rings.
C环里面还有D环
There is a ring interior to the C-ring called the D-ring.
当我们的先驱者号到达土星 发现了最美丽的F环
And once we got there with Voyager, showed us the F-ring in all its glory.
在F环外还有微弱的E环和G环
And then there were some diffuse rings outside, the E and the G-ring.
每条环的性质都不一样
Each of these rings has a different personality.
A环几乎是透明的
The A-ring is almost transparent,
因为光线最容易穿透A环
which is why light easily passes through it.
B环密度最大 充满物质
The B-ring is dense, chock-full of material.
C环比A环还透明
The C-ring is even more transparent than the A.
而那儿是D环
While the D-ring is barely there.
这些环里面有许多令人感兴趣的
There's a lot of neat things in those rings.
我们认为他们都是不同的
So you can't think of them as homogeneous body.
你可以想象一下这些由各种碎片组成的环
You gotta think of  each particle inside those rings and what is ***
就像我们所见颜色 形状和阴影各不相同
These distinct qualities are what we see as colours, shapes and shadows.
神奇的土星光环
The wonder that is Saturn's rings.
我们能够看见它是因为
The reason we can see them at all is due to the Sun,
它像月亮一样反射阳光
Just as our moon glows with reflected sunlight,
这是土星光环如此明亮的原因
So these Saturn's rings.
这个现象称为环反射
It is a phenomenon called"ring shine".
想象一下你在土星背面的黑夜中抬头仰望
Just imagine yourself on the night side of Saturn looking up,
看见这些光环布满整个天空
and having the rings just completely covering the sky.
比地球上的满月亮很多
so do Saturn's rings. It's much brighter than ** the Earth on a full moon.
闪耀着 非常明亮
They shimmer, and they're brilliant and they're bright,
这主要是由于环由冰质碎片组成
and that's because they're mostly made up of ice particles
反射了更多的阳光
which reflect a lot of sunlight.
然而有迹象表明
However, there is evidence
这种太阳系奇观
that the glowing marvels of our Solar System
也许不是永恒的
won't be around forever.
一些科学家猜测光环可能在某时消失
Some scientists are asking just when will they disappear.
尽管科学家们对于土星光环
For all scientists know about Saturn's rings,
依然还有很多不明之处
they remain a huge mystery.
这种猜想也受到质疑
When they appeared is a point of much debate.
他们认为环形成于土星诞生时
Scientists used to believe that the rings were formed at the same time as Saturn.
约45亿年前
4.5 billion years ago.
但是我们无法知道环上的物质 还有哪些是最初形成时的
But because we don't understand what holds the rings together
我们最多只能猜测环还能坚持多久
and our best guess as to how long the rings could stay together
也许还能存在几亿年吧
is only a hundred million years, there's something wrong with this picture.
有理由相信
There are reasons to believe
土星环的寿命不会超过几亿年了
they're no older than a few hundred million years old.
这个理由出自
Those reasons lie in trying to estimate
对环磨损消耗速度的预计
how much erosion is taking place on the rings,
因为小陨石的不断袭击
because of the hailstorm of micro-meteorites,
那些高速飞来的微小陨石
small, tiny bodies… particles
袭击并损耗土星环
that come in at a tremendous speed and chip away at the rings and therefore erode them.
天王星 海王星和木星都有自己的环
Neptune, Uranus and Jupiter also have rings,
只是比较少和微弱
but theirs are sparse and dim.
土星环是最明亮完整的
Saturn's are bright and full,
这导致科学家们思索
leading scientists to suggest
土星环可能没有被侵蚀太久
that they haven't been exposed to erosion for long.
也就是说 相对还很新
And therefore are relatively new.
但是 不断的侵蚀
But, does this gradual erosion
是否意味着土星最终将失去着最大的特征？
mean that Saturn will lose its most magnificent feature?
这种想法认为长时间以来
The idea is that over long periods of time
环的物质碎片将越来越碎小
the material can get just so small that it can be charged,
如果你进入土星的磁力层
and acquiring a charge in Saturn's magnetosphere,
会被磁力场拉出土星
and then it can just get zipped away, taken away by the magnetic field.
或者直接螺旋形掉进土星
Or it just spirals into Saturn itself.
这是土星环的死亡阶段
That is a scenario for the death of the rings,
将被慢慢消耗掉
it's that they finally get eroded away.
因此土星环
In order for Saturn to continuously have rings,
需要不断的补充
they need to be re-filled.
当前的土星环如此巨大
For the moment Saturn has a tremendously large ring system,
但环的组成物质需要不断补充
but the actual material in the rings does have to be replenished.
这样看来 另一种形式的袭击似乎是必须的
Strangely, another kind of assault might be necessary
才能维持环的存在
to preserve them.
必须要有彗星击中土星环
They have to get renewed by an errant comet coming in and crashing,
给环提供新的物质
adding to the mass that's going around there.
这个问题备受怀疑
The debate continues
环消失的理论在建立过程中始终充满争议
when theorising as to when the ring will vanish.And that kind of question is still being debated.
需要几亿年或几十亿年 我不能确定
Hundreds of millions of years, probably, maybe billions of years, we don't know.
这个课题一直在讨论中
That's a matter of debate right now.
环到底是很年轻 然后很快就死亡
Whether the rings are young and are gonna die an early death,
还是已经存在很久了 也将继续存在很久很久
or they're old and they're gonna remain with us for a very, very long time.
土星的48颗卫星中 某些小卫星
Of Saturn's 48 named moons, there are small moons
被称作"牧羊犬"卫星
called"shepherds", for a good reason.
引力作用下他们围绕着某条土星环
They have gravitational pulls that help keep the rings intact
放牧
by herding the particles.
土星专家们被这土星的卫星和环之间复杂精巧的编排所吸引
Saturn's experts are interested in the complicated choreography between the planet's moons and its rings.
扭曲麻花般的F环特别引人关注
The contorted F-ring is especially intriguing.
两个牧羊犬卫星环绕在两边 普罗米修斯(土卫16)和潘多拉(土卫17)
And then there's the two shepherd satellites on either side, Prometheus and Pandora,
环被卫星引力作用
and they are having gravitational effects on this ring.
拉向几个方向
It's being tugged in a variety of directions,
看起来影响非常剧烈
so it looks wild and misbehaved, if you will,
这是动力变化作用区域
and it's a dynamicists playground.
我们对F环发生的这一切非常感兴趣
We're very, very interested in watching what happens to the F-ring
因为这展示了卫星与环之间的相互作用
because it tells us how moons interact with rings.
土星早在公元前700年的古文明中被记载
Saturn mesmerized civilizations as early as 700 BCE,
亚述人记录了星空中明亮的土星
when the Assyrians took note of it sparkling in the distant sky.
数百年后希腊人称之(克洛诺斯)
Hundreds of years later, the Greeks gave it a name: Cronos,
收获之神
after the god of harvest.
可能由于土星在收获的季节里处于天堂的位置
Possibly due to its position in the sky during harvest season.
土星又是罗马神话的农业之神
The Romans' god of agriculture was Saturnus,
这就是现在土星的含义
which is why we call it Saturn.
也是由一星期的第六天来命名
They also named a day of the week after him,
英语里的星期六
what we now call Saturday.
不过 如果罗马人近距离观察土星
However, had the Romans actually seen the planet close up,
可能会称之为天气之神
they might have named it for the god of weather.
土星是一个狂热之处 时刻变化着
Saturn is a wild, ever-changing place but,
不像地球上的天气
unlike on Earth where things change
通常只持续几天或几小时
on a daily and even on an hourly basis,
土星风暴能持续几天 几周甚至几个月
the storms on Saturn can last for days and weeks and months…
缓慢变化的巨大范围的天气
and things change on a large scale very slowly over time.
土星剧烈天气现象的发现
The discovery of this violent activity on Saturn
惊动了专家们
came as a surprise to experts.
几个世纪以来 对土星的观测都不是那么清晰
For centuries, their view of the planet had been obscured
土星大气中的大片氨气阻碍了观测
by an ammonia gas haze.
新的卫星数据改变了这一切
New satellite data is changing everything.
现在我们知道土星活力十足
And we see now that Saturn is a dynamic place.
被证明甚至比木星还要活跃的多
It's been revealed now as being probably more dynamic in a lot of ways than Jupiter.
仅仅就我们已经看到的那些风暴
There's the number of storms we see, the motions that they do…
风暴的风速达到惊人的1000英里每小时(1600千米每小时)
Incredibly, winds blow at speeds of 1,000 mph.
实际的测量风暴
We measure the winds literally
需要观察小块的气体移动图像
by watching the different little cells of the atmosphere move in imaging.
因此从拍摄的图像
So you need sequential images
看看这些是怎样快速移动的
to see how much things have moved.
土星表面没有山
There are no mountains on the surface of Saturn,
仔细看看这些云的面貌
its cloud features that we look at to see how quickly
如何快速地变化 运动形成飓风
they evolve and change and move to measure the winds.
最近的探索显示出
Recent exploration has shown
一些目前难以理解的现象
other phenomena that aren't yet understood.
我们可以看见这些面貌 云团和漩涡
We can see features, clouds, eddies,
像木星上那样的巨大的条状物体
big plumes of material like we see on Jupiter.
可以看见其中的很多椭圆风暴
And we see these oval storms, lots of them,
实际上在南半球的这个纬度段里
and in fact is one latitude in the Southern hemisphere
有许多风暴
where lots of storms zip around…disband,
可以观测到他们的产生
and we've watched them be created,
可以看到其中一些合并消失了
we've seen them die, they die by merging.
科学家们昵称之风暴巷道
Scientists nicknamed this area"Storm Alley",
有半个美国西边大
after a region in America's Midwest
造成剧烈气象
that produces violent weather.
相信这里也存在着闪电
It is believed there's lightning there,
不过目前还没有被发现
though no one has seen it.
是因为技术上的原因
And there's a technical reason for that,
闪电需要在黑夜中观察
to see the lightning you'd have to get around on the night side,
因为闪电的亮度不是太大
and because the lightning ** aren't all that bright,
必须在黑暗中观察
so you need the darkness.
但是土星的黑夜十分明亮
But the night side of Saturn is very bright
由于土星光环
because of all the ring light
把土星夜晚照耀得如此明亮
that shines down on the night side of Saturn and so…
要辨别云层中的闪电十分困难
it's very hard to sort the lightning from just puffy little clouds.
土星大气更是令人惊奇
The hellish weather on Saturn has one more astounding surprise,
简直就是个怪物
and is a true monster.
某个土星奇异风暴
One of the freakiest storms on Saturn
南极上的飓风
was this hurricane-like thing that they found down at the South pole.
风暴面积比美国还大
This storm is bigger than the US.
而木星上的那个大红斑也是风暴
The great red spot on Jupiter is merely hurricane-like.
是个没有眼的风暴
That storm doesn't have an eyewall.
然而这个南极土星大风暴
However, the South pole storm
跟地球上的飓风特点一样
has the characteristics of a terrestrial hurricane,
它有个眼
including an eyewall,
是地球外唯一的有眼风暴
making it the only such storm on another planet.
还不确切是否是跟地球上一样的飓风
It's not clear that it is a hurricane in every sense like we have here on Earth.
不过目前从形态上来看
But so far, the morphology of it
非常像一个地球飓风
looks very much like a hurricane.
这非常令人激动  每个人都为之兴奋不已
That was very exciting, everyone got very excited about that,
我们被震惊了
it even surprised us.
你可以从这个飓风眼中看过去就像在地球上那样
And you can see right down into the eye, just as you can with a hurricane on Earth,
能看到土星大气中更多的气象
and they can see farther into Saturn's atmosphere
这些一直经常发生的气象
than they've ever been able to see before.
这真是土星之窗
So this thing is literally a window into Saturn.
很惊人的发现一些气象与地球上的十分相似
And it's amazing to see something so similar to Earth
我们可以对之做一些研究
on Saturn and then find out that we can actually do some science because of it.
南极大风暴据测有5000英里(8000千米)宽
The South pole storm measures 5,000 mile across,
2/3个地球的直径大
that's 2/3 the diameter of the Earth.
如果一个极其强大的风暴产生于地球
If a hurricane that huge were to form here,
距离跨越纽约到巴格达
it would cover a distance from New York city to Baghdad,
将摧毁这之间的一切
annihilating all in its path.
飓风围绕其中心的眼漩涡型旋转
It basically is a swirling vortex of air that is centred around a hole,
就像围墙围着这个中心
and right at the centre, where with an eyewall around it.
还不知道是什么导致这么巨大的风暴
What powers this monster storm is still unknown.
土星的风暴比地球上强大很多
And the winds are stronger on Saturn than they are in Earth,
这真是一个迷
which is a puzzle in itself,
土星受到的太阳能很低 自身也没有释放多少能量
because Saturn gets so little energy from either the Sun or from its own inside.
风暴发生在南极中央而不是赤道附近
It's centred around the South pole of Saturn rather than being
异于地球上的风暴
in the equatorial region, like a hurricane on Earth would be.
2007年初现代图像采集技术
In early 2007, modern imaging technology
揭示了更多土星上令科学家们震惊的东西
revealed something else on Saturn that astounded scientists.
我们对它兴趣更浓了
We see it very intensely now.
它如此大和奇怪
It's something big, something strange…
我从来没有在宇宙其他地方见过
and something never seen in the Universe before.
土星 太阳系中奇怪而又最美丽的行星
Saturn, the Solar System's most bizarre yet beautiful planet
越来越充满了神秘
has just gotten even more mysterious.
1979年先驱者号探测器
In 1979, the Voyager spacecraft
显示出土星北极的完美几何形状
showed a perfect geometric form over the North Pole.
2006年10月
In October 2006,
卡西尼探测器发现它还在那儿
the Cassini craft found that it is still there.
很奇怪它还在那儿 没有移动
It's just bizarre. It sits there kind of still, it doesn't move with the planet.
极地形似一个六边形
The Pole has a hexagonal feature,
6条边围绕着北极
a six-sided polygon that encircles the pole
大约在北纬78度的位置
at about 78°North latitude,
特点就是 它一直固定在那儿
and it's sitting there as a set feature.
这六边形有点像地球上的极地漩涡
The hexagon is similar to Earth's polar vortex
长时间固定形状地在极地周围吹
which has winds blowing in a circular fashion around the pole.
土星漩涡大到可以塞下4个地球
Saturn's vortex can fit 4 Earths inside of it,
在土星云层里延伸60英里深
and extends 60 miles deep into Saturn's clouds.
非常奇怪的是航海者号发现一小片云在其中100/米秒旋转
And what's more bizarre, Voyager saw little, tiny clouds going around at about 100 meters per second,
以200英里每小时(320千米每小时)的速度在六边形里旋转
which is about 200 mph, going around this racetrack.
专家认为这只是一种短暂的现象
People thought,"Well, maybe they're just a temporary thing,
那儿的漩涡怎么形成的？
"how could this stay there?"
在那里持续了至少20年 这到底是什么？
It's stayed there now for at least 20 years, and we're going,"What is this?"
如果在那儿 你钻进土星厚云层
If you go there you're gonna enter these thick clouds,
越深气体密度越大 大气压越强
and the deeper you go the more intense the pressure's gonna get,
超过某个深度你会内爆
to a point when you just implode.
你和你的太空船无法继续前进
You and your spacecraft can't make it any farther.
目前探测器环绕土星
For now, visits to Saturn's orbit
作为土星的人造卫星使用
are reserved for unmanned spacecrafts.
这里至少已经有48颗天然卫星
But surrounding the planet are at least 48 moons.
冒险登陆某个卫星则具有可行性
Venturing to one of those is more feasible.
我们去土星的一个大兴趣点
What's interesting now that we're going to these planets,
是探索那些卫星们
is that we're learning that in some ways
热闹的卫星大团聚
the moons are where the action is.
我们去过了其中的一个
We've already been to one of them.
提坦(土卫六)是除了月球外 唯一探索过的卫星
Titan is the only moon other than our own to have been explored.
这次探索意义非常重大
The event was beyond significant.
2005年1月14日
On January 14th, 2005,
科幻成为了现实
science-fiction became fact.
作为正在土星执行的卡西尼任务的一部分
As part of the ongoing Cassini mission to Saturn,
惠更斯号无人探测器
the unmanned Huygens probe
降落到这个最大土星卫星表面
descended onto the surface of Saturn's biggest moon.
提坦(土卫六)星如其名 有水星那么大
Titan lives up to its name. It is the size of the planet Mercury.
实际上是太阳系中第二大的卫星
In fact, it is the second largest moon in the Solar System.
比月球大一半
50% bigger than our Moon.
很多方面都吸引着人
It is seductive in many ways.
一方面土卫六非常像地球
For one, Titan looks much like Earth.
过程非常让我激动
That was the thing that beat me over the head, just how…
逐渐接近土卫六的地面的过程
remarkably similar in process the surface of Titan looked.
看见的河流 湖床 还有风
We have river channels that feed into these lake beds, we have winds.
来另个区域又看见了沙丘
And then in other areas we have dunes.
在土卫六的赤道地区
The equator region of Titan,
收到了质量很高的雷达图像
at least on one side where we've gotten good radar imagery,
数百个隔着数百英里的沙丘
has hundreds and hundreds of miles of these dunes,
沙丘有几百米高 分别隔着几英里
that are hundreds of meters high, several miles apart,
简直就是沙丘海洋
and they just go on, this vast sea of dunes.
也许是固体碳氢化合物颗粒堆积成的
There are possibly deposits of solid hydro-carbons.
只有等探测器降落下去了
And we didn't really know until that probe landed
才知道到底是降落在液态还是固态地表上
whether it was gonna hit liquid or some solid surface.
看起来像掉到了布丁上
It seemed to kind of fall on what looks like a kind of pudding,
既不是液态也不是固态
it doesn't seem to be liquid or solid.
土卫六的表面似乎附着一些粘稠物质
It seems that Titan has some goo on the surface.
既不是陆地也不是海
That's almost kind of neither land nor sea,
而是介于其间的 非常令人惊讶
but something in between. That's very amazing.
惊奇的是土卫六像地球一样有着大气
Amazingly, Titan, like Earth, has an extended atmosphere.
太阳系没有其他任何卫星有大气
No other moon does in our Solar System.
土卫六大气很浓密很厚
The atmosphere of Titan is very, very thick and massive.
是地球大气的10倍质量
It has a mass that's 10 times the mass of the Earth's atmosphere.
这是一层非常非常厚的气体
So you have a very thick layer of gases,
比其他我们所知道的大气都要厚
thicker than the air as we know it.
大气中的微粒十分小
The particles in the air are also very small,
使得看起来比较模糊
so I would characterize them more .
像雾或者云那样
as a haze than as a fog or clouds
雾有200英里(320千米)厚 完全不同与地球上的云
The haze is 200 miles thick resembling something else on Earth.
从外面看上去像一个完全不透明的大桔子
From the outside, it appears essentially opaque, like a big, orange ball.
但是随着惠更斯探测器穿越大气
But as the Huygens probe descended through the atmosphere,
开始变得透明起来
it's transparent enough
可以看清降落区域的地表特征
to be able to see the surface features as it fell through.
跟洛杉矶的大雾没有太大不同
But it's not unlike a hazy day here in Los Angeles.
不是土卫六大气的颜色吸引科学家
It's not the colour of the atmosphere that most intrigues scientists,
而是其成分
it's the composition.
氮气和甲烷
Nitrogen and methane,
正是早期地球大气的主要成分
the same gases they believe made up much of Earth's early atmosphere.
认为土卫六的大气
The idea that Titan's atmosphere
跟40亿年前的地球大气很相似
mimics the atmosphere of early Earth 4 billion years ago,
激动着我们 让人很兴奋
it's something we're very, very excited about and interested in.
这是我们在实验室做过的最困难的实验
And it's one of the things we're studying very hard in our laboratory.
看看是否能得到期待的结果
Let's see if we can get this aligned. What do we have?
科罗拉多州立大学 玛格丽特·托尔伯特博士
At the University of Colorado, Dr. Margaret Tolbert
正在她的实验室里模拟土卫六大气
is simulating Titan's atmosphere in her lab.
是否其中包含着生命形成所需的元素？
Might it too have the necessary ingredients for life?
在这个实验里 尽量模拟土卫六
In this experiment we're trying to simulate the chemistry
大气顶部的气体成分
that goes on high in Titan's atmosphere,
也就是大雾之处
where the haze is forming.
这里有个反应室
So what we have is a reaction chamber here,
里面充满了氮气和甲烷
and all that we have here is nitrogen and methane.
土卫六大气的主要成分
So the two most important components of Titan's atmosphere.
然后我们只亮一盏灯
And then we're just gonna flick on a lamp,
这盏灯模拟太阳照射到土卫六大气上
and that lamp is going to simulate the sunlight hitting Titan's atmosphere.
托尔伯特博士的研究令人惊讶地
Incredibly, Tolbert's research has shown
显示出土卫六的大气
that Titan's atmosphere,
在模拟的阳光下
when stimulated by sunlight,
开始产生一些有机化合物
begins to produce organic compounds.
这对于科学家在地球外寻找生物
For scientists looking for life beyond our planet,
非常的有帮助
this could be big.
当科学家们在银河系里寻找生命的迹象时
As scientists scour the galaxy for signs of life,
这些令人激动的结果来自太阳系
there are some exciting results from within our own Solar System.
土卫六应该含有这些生命必需的物质
Saturn's moon, Titan, seems to have the necessary ingredients.
科罗拉多州立大学的实验表明阳光和富含氮气 甲烷的土卫六大气共同作用
Testing at the University of Colorado has shown that when sunlight interacts with Titan's nitrogen and methane-rich atmosphere,
产生有机化合物
organic compounds are created.
这些有机物
So these organics are
飘浮在土卫六表面
floating down to the surface of Titan,
就像图片中那些
and you can see them in the pictures,
谁又知道这些化合物会创造出什么呢
and who knows what they're doing once they're there?
也许能创造某些新形式的生命
They could be providing energy to some new kind of life.
还需要做更多的研究
Further research is needed
测定土卫六上是否真的有生命
to determine if there really is life on Titan.
或者能在某时进化出生命
Or if it might some day develop.
尽管土卫六大气非常相似早期地球大气
Although its atmosphere resembles early Earth,
但还是有很大不同
the environment is vastly different.
这里很冷
It's cold.
低于零下华氏300度(-150度)
It's -300 ℉
没有液态水
and there's no liquid water.
这是土卫六和早期地球的最大不同
So that's a big difference between early Earth and Titan.
土卫六上的河床和湖床
The lakes and river beds on Titan
是另外一些东西开凿的
were carved down to the ground by something.
这里没有液态水
There's no liquid water on the moon,
那么 是什么在这里流动？
so what flows on this terrain?
地球上的山是硅酸盐石块构成
The hills on Earth are made of silicate, rocks…
而土卫六上的山由冰和固态甲烷构成
whereas the hills on Titan are ice, methane ice…
河道是甲烷雨造成的
The river channels on Titan are formed by methane rain,
不同于地球上流水形成的河谷
as opposed to the Earth river valleys formed by water.
显然 这里下着液态的甲烷雨
Liquid methane, it seems, rains down on Titan,
或者曾经下过
or did at one time.
土卫六温度太低一些气体都液化了
On Titan, it is so cold that gases liquefied.
就有了河流湖泊
And there are coastlines and rivers,
这些地面河流都由
and all this terrain shaped
液态甲烷构成
by moving rivers of methane.
这些非常令人好奇
It's just completely intriguing.
甲烷是天然气的主要成分  还包含一些丙烷和丁烷
Methane is the principal component of natural gas, butane and propane.
都是能源
All sources of fuel.
含碳油气都是燃料
There's a lot of hydrocarbons,
土星六上发现的就是这些
it might be very light hydrocarbons, on Titan.
含量很多
And there's a lot of it.
只要有氧可以永远燃烧下去
And it burns if you put it in contact with oxygen,
那里能量非常之多
so there's a lot of energy out there.
卫星表面的这么多能量
Enough on the surface of this huge moon,
可以满足很长时间人类的需求
to supply all of Earth's needs for a very long time.
土卫六天然气储量非常大
Here is this tremendous supply of natural gas on Titan.
能都带回地球那就太棒了
Well, wouldn't it be great to go out there and tap into it and bring it back?
但我想这将耗资巨大
But I think that you would find that it would cost you so much to go out
把甲烷提取并带回来
and get the methane and bring it back,
实际上你带不回任何东西
that you would never be able to effectively power anything on Earth with it.
尽管土卫六是土星最大的卫星
While Titan is Saturn's largest moon,
不过某个小卫星也许更令人激动
one of its smallest may be even more exciting.
土卫二 由明亮的冰岩混合组成
It's a brilliant ball of ice and rock called Enceladus.
它比较小
It's a tiny object,
直径只有300英里(480千米)
it's only about 300 miles in size.
体积只有月球的1/8
That's about 1/8th the size of our own Moon.
我们从没见过如此小的天体
And we've never seen a body that small
居然是活跃的
that has activity on it.
2005年发现了它的活力
This activity was discovered in 2005
由卡西尼成像团队的卡罗林·帕科博士发现
by Dr. Carolyn Porco and her Cassini imaging team.
一幅照片上显示土卫二像个喷气式发动机
One photo seemed to suggest that jets were coming out of Enceladus.
在我们团队看来很可能
It seemed very likely to the members of my team that it's possible
这个喷气式发动机是个间歇喷泉
that these jets are actually geysers,
喷射水汽
they're erupting from pockets of liquid water
喷气位置离表面不深
not too far beneath the surface.
地球上与土卫二最相近的应该是
The closest thing we have on Earth to Enceladus
黄石国家公园的老实间歇泉
is something like Old Faithful geyser here at Yellowstone National Park,
能把水汽喷上约100英尺(45米)高
which is shooting water vapour and water about 150 ft into the air.
而土卫二上的蒸汽喷泉能
The geysers on Enceladus are erupting
在空中喷出几百英里高
water vapour hundreds or miles into the air
是由于喷射猛烈而又没有大气阻碍
because there's much lower gravity there and the fact there's no atmosphere holding them in.
土卫二上被发现的很多喷泉
Many geysers have since been discovered,
都位于南半球的一个区域内
all in a region of Enceladus' southern hemisphere.
产生于那些裂缝
They are coming out of these fissures,
这些巨大裂缝延伸有135千米长
big cracks that go on for about 135 kilometres.
一些80英里长的裂缝
Something like 80 miles of cracks.
我们称之"老虎纹"
We call them"tiger stripes",
因为我们第一次看见的时候
because when we first saw them
发现这些纹路非常像老虎身上的
they really looked like the stripes on a tiger.
有4个区域布满裂缝
There're four areas that seem to be ridges
应该都是地质活跃地区
or kind of active geologic areas.
这些区域喷射的水汽柱
And the plumes seemed to be coming out of these areas
大约有20或21根
and we counted about 20 or 21 plumes.
土卫二的南面都被宇宙级的老实泉覆盖
Southern Enceladus is covered in cosmic Old Faithfuls.
谁能想到一个德克萨斯州大的冰球
Who would have thought that an ice ball of the size of Texas
活力十足 不停喷发水柱和水汽
would be alive with plumes and geysers?
太令人惊异了
I mean, it's astounding.
土卫二由于土星的潮汐作用而被加热
Enceladus is heated in its interior by the tides of Saturn.
月球引力作用于地球海洋
The Earth's Moon is pulling on the Earth's oceans
拉升而造成潮汐现象
and distorting their shape and producing the tides
这些现象我们很熟悉
that we're familiar with here on Earth.
不过土卫二在土星强大引力作用下
But on Enceladus, the planet Saturn is pulling on that moon
在围绕土星旋转的同时
and as Enceladus goes around in its orbit,
由于引力方向不断变化
that pull is changing the ice inside Enceladus.
土卫二内部不断碎裂摩擦
It's creaking and groaning and rubbing against itself
产生大量热量
and creating a lot of heat through friction.
我们认为这潮汐摩擦生成的热
We think it's that frictional heat
使冰水蒸发
that is producing the evaporation of the water ice that
从地表裂缝中逃逸 形成了我们所见的喷泉
is then escaping through these cracks and making the geysers that we see there.
另外
And there's more.
土卫二的喷发 证实了另一个理论
Enceladus' eruptions have clarified a theory
关于土星某个环的形成原因
of what powers one of Saturn's rings.
我们了解到土卫二的喷发
We knew there might be jets,
把他表面的物质抛离
something coming from the surface
并围绕土星旋转而形成了E环
that was injecting material into orbit around Saturn to form the E-ring.
E环离土星最远
The E-ring is furthest from the planet,
约74000英里(120000千米)
about 74,000 miles away.
这个环绕距离
It happens to be just at the same orbit,
刚好约等于土卫二跟土星的距离
the same distance from Saturn as Enceladus.
因此 刚好表明
And so it really suggests
E环来自于土卫二
that owes its origin to Enceladus.
E环的厚度
And the thickness of the E-ring
形成它的那些物质
sort of matches the thickness
都是从土卫二南极喷出的
of particles that were ejected from the South Pole of Enceladus.
如果这些喷泉消失
If these geysers disappear,
E环也会跟着消失
so might the ring.
喷射水汽表明
Ultimately the liquid jets suggest
土卫二含有很多水
that there is water on Enceladus.
这说明很多问题
And perhaps something else.
研究这些水
So the search for water is not,
不是因为某天我们太渴而要喝这些水
"Oh, one day we'll be thirsty so we'll have something to drink,"
研究这些水的动力是
the search for water is guided
因为我们寻找生命的兴趣
by our interest in the search for life.
很简单 因为水
It's that simple: follow the water.
土卫二是最令人激动
Saturn's moon Enceladus is one of the most exciting
也是目前太阳系中我们了解最少的
and least understood places in our Solar System.
土卫二是个奇怪的地方
Enceladus is a really strange place.
最奇怪的是它引人注目的明亮
The strangest thing that got people's attention first is it's very bright,
是太阳系中最明亮的小星体
it's the whitest object in the Solar System.
现在我们认识到这都是冰雪覆盖表面的原因
And we now realize that it is covered in freshly fallen snow
雪是由落回地面的水汽形成
which is the ice that's fallen back from these geysers onto the surface.
这些冰雪让科学家们兴奋
And it's that ice that has scientists excited.
那里的一切可能性都令人激动
Possibilities there are amazing.
在太阳系中寻找水
The search for water in our Solar System
最终是为了寻找生命
is ultimately a search for life.
寻找水以期望其中有生命
You look for water in the hopes that maybe there will be life.
由于冰的发现
Because of the presence of ice,
一些专家认为外星生物的发现
some experts believe the search for alien life
将从土卫二上开始
should begin on Enceladus.
还有很多更令人惊奇的其他物质分子
It has a lot of other molecules in it, a lot of exotic things
可能就像这显示的
which show us that there's probably
地底下的含水化合物不断运动
aqueous chemistry going on under ground.
如果有大量化学反应发生
So there's a lot of little percolating kind of chemistry going on and maybe
也许能够进化出生物 因此 我们应该去那看看
you could get biology, maybe, so maybe we should go look.
它是行星探索的一种圣杯
This is kind of the Holy Grail
在现代 出发并寻找
of modern-day planetary exploration, to go and seek out
太阳系的这些区域
those environments in the Solar System
这些可能拥有生命的区域
where life might possibly have gotten started.
然后刚好遇见了土卫二
And we just stumbled upon it.
激动人心？当然了
Is that exciting? Of course it's exciting.
对于每一位或者的科学家都如此
It's the kind of thing scientists live for.
能够了解那些气体的成分
We know of the composition of the gases that are coming out
是因为我们的太空船穿越其中
because we've flown through them with the spacecraft.
那里面包含碳和氮
And we've got the composition including carbon and nitrogen
还有其他一些生命进化所必需的物质
and all those goodies that you need to make life.
我们知道这里也有能源
And then we know there's a source of energy
由潮汐摩擦带来的热
from the frictional heat of the tidal heat
可以看见表面冒出来的那些热气
in the interior, and we can see the heat on the surface.
于是这所有的因素
So all the elements are there
全部在这里集中以支持生命诞生
that might be sufficient to sustain life
如果这里真的有的话
if life could've got started there.
这就是土卫二最令人感兴趣的地方
So that makes Enceladus a very exciting place.
不过到底是何种形式的生命？
But what kind of life?
我们可不是在谈论寿司
We're not talking sushi,
不是龙虾和鱼 我们说的是微生物
we're not talking lobsters and fish, we're talking microbes.
对于土卫二我想我们最多只能期待这么多
I think that's about the best that we can hope for on a moon like Enceladus.
如果你在太阳系内有幸发现一种生物
If we ever discover such life in our Solar System, it's gonna be
简单的 像细菌那样的
the simplest possible, it's gonna be bacterial or something like it.
即便是发现如此小的东西
Even the discovery of something small,
那也是非同寻常的大事
would be a huge event.
将改变我们对太阳系的认识
It would change everything that we think and know about our Solar System,
对宇宙和我们自身的认识
the Universe and ourselves.
大部分对土星和其卫星的了解
Much of what is known about Saturn and its moons
都来源于卡西尼号人造土星卫星
has come from the Cassini satellite,
于2004年进入土星轨道
that was inserted into the planet's orbit in 2004.
目前正绕着土星旋转 观测土星环 卫星和土星自身
It is currently touring its rings, moons, and the planet itself.
2008年卡西尼号会绕土星旋转70周
By 2008, Cassini will have made 70 trips around the gas giant.
它会在那儿围绕着土星旋转
Putting an orbiter around the planet
坚守在那儿
and being able to hang out there,
观测土星系统的任何不同的情况
and monitor the system and all its different elements
在很长一段时间
for a long period of time,
最佳途径就是通过它研究这些星体
that's the best way to study these bodies.
科学家们需要处理许多日常信息
Scientists on a daily basis
来自于这对"亲密接触"者
process the information sent back from these"close encounters".
在镜头旁有个雷达
In addition to the camera there there's a radar
发射无线电波穿过云层
that can send its radiowaves through the clouds
然后接收表面返回波并绘制图像
and get an echo of the surface and make an image of the surface.
另外使用分光仪测量成分
And there are spectrometers to measure the composition,
用红外线设备测量温度
and other infrared devices to measure temperature.
这是一艘完美的太空船
So it's a very comprehensive spacecraft.
看到更多 了解更多
As you see better, you learn more.
就像瑜伽熊说的那样
I think it may have been Yoghi bear who said,
只要你认真看 你会发现很多
"You can see a lot just by looking".
把相关信息和地球上比较
Relating this information to processes on Earth
有助于解释地球的一些神秘现象
could help explain mysteries of our own planet.
土星很不同于地球
Saturn is really very different from the Earth,
直径比地球大8 9倍
its diameter is 8 or 9 times greater than that of the Earth.
完全由氢气构成的大气
Its atmosphere is made of hydrogen,
完全不同于我们的大气
completely different from our own atmosphere.
不过同样的物理规律作用着 同样的力量控制这土星气象
But the same physics is going on, the same forces are controlling
也控制着地球气象
the weather on Saturn as are controlling the weather on Earth.
这是我们历史的一部分 是我们太阳系
It is part of our history, it's the Solar System.
我开始知道太阳系是如何形成的
So understanding how our Solar System formed
真正知道我为什么在这里
is really understanding how I got here.
了解太阳系其他行星的情况
And understanding the nature of other planets in the Solar System,
都是我们的邻居
they're like my neighbours.
卡西尼号的新技术
Cassini's new imaging technologies,
让我们看到以前没有看到的景象
are giving us never before seen views and information
在每一天
by the day.
卡西尼号与土星的亲密接触
Cassini's close encounters with Saturn
带领我们近距离观察它的秘密
will bring us nearer to unlocking its secrets.
很多复杂的事情需要我们很长时间去解释它
It's quite complex and it will take us a long time to figure it all out.
我想我们现在还不是完全了解土星
I don't think we ever will figure all of it out,
这真是件愉快的事情 能够环绕和
but it's just the beauty of being able to be in orbit
观测这样一个富饶的土星系统
and monitor a rich planetary system like Saturn's.
地球在宇宙中并不孤独
The Earth has a context in the rest of the Universe.
如果你想了解宇宙别处
And, you want to know where we fit in the Universe?
不要只研究地球
You don't get the answer to that just studying the Earth itself.
即使我们已经了解了光环王者很多很多
For, as much as we discover about the Lord of the Rings.
它永远激励着我们
it will always inspire us.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing